<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Theory on Corey Stone</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Theory on Corey Stone</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Privacy &#34;harms&#34; and why they matter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/privacy-harms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/privacy-harms/</guid>
      <description>A look at the dangers that result when privacy protections don&amp;#39;t protect.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>What is the point of a privacy program? Is it to avoid <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1170520/worldwide-data-breach-fines-settlements/">whopping legal penalties</a>? To prevent the <a href="https://www.varonis.com/blog/company-reputation-after-a-data-breach">tarnished reputation</a> that comes with being in the news for the wrong reasons? Or even to comply with a <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3782222">consent decree</a>?</p>
<p>For some companies, any of these reasons might certainly be the case &ndash; and that&rsquo;s perfectly fine and arguably mutually beneficial for both companies and consumers alike (when done right). But, for the sake of discussion, allow me to put all of that to the side and think about privacy on a more fundamental, personal level. Of course, the point of a privacy program is to protect and preserve user privacy &ndash; but <em>why?</em></p>
<p>Why else should we care about user privacy, even if the user themselves might not understand or care?</p>
<p>I recently read a brilliant paper titled <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3782222"><em>Privacy Harms</em></a> by Danielle Citron and Daniel Solove. One of the goals of the paper is to outline the risks and damages that can result from the misuse, mishandling, and insufficient protection of personal information which they refer to as &ldquo;harms&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In the paper, Citron and Solove take a legal approach to help courts better understand and effectively adjudicate cases that relate to privacy, where courts currently have a myopic focus on clear, explicit monetary loss or injury to enforce violations of privacy. To do so, Citron and Solove define a &ldquo;typology&rdquo; of privacy harms that can transpire from privacy violations.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite the word. For the uninitiated (i.e, myself), what is a typology? Per the <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/typology">Merriam-Webster dictionary</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Typology (n)</strong> <em>[the] study of or analysis or classification based on types or categories</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>With that established, let&rsquo;s continue and see how this might help us better understand (and protect) privacy.</p>
<h2 id="some-context">Some context</h2>
<p>Citron and Solove&rsquo;s paper is heavily grounded in law and this topic carries with it legal implications that are far beyond my qualifications. I am not a lawyer, even if I have passed the <a href="https://iapp.org/certify/cippus/">CIPP/US</a>. That said, I am not going to focus on the legal aspect of this paper, but it is important to provide some context for the rest of the post.</p>
<p>The idea of a &ldquo;harm&rdquo; comes to us from the legal world, as part of a broader concept called a <strong>tort</strong>, defined by the Cornell&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/tort">Legal Information Institute</a> as &ldquo;an act or omission that gives rise to injury or harm to another and amounts to a civil wrong for which courts impose liability&rdquo;. Simply put: being able to demonstrate some damage has occurred, like your car being totaled after an accident, which lays the groundwork for an entity to be sued (liable) in court is what constitutes a tort.</p>
<p>However, current caselaw is woefully unprepared and inept at acknowledging harms resulting from privacy violations because they do not fall under the umbrella of what are pre-established &ldquo;cognizable&rdquo; (recognized) harms. A harm to you or me, like being unable to buy a new car because <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TransUnion_LLC_v._Ramirez">your credit report says you are a terrorist</a>, or receiving spam emails because your bank violated its own privacy policy and <a href="https://casetext.com/case/cherny-v-emigrant-bank">shared your email address with third-parties</a>, is not the same kind of harm to the courts. If your identity was stolen after you were victim to a data breach, good luck putting two and two together in court to establish causality. And if you are worried that your identity <em>will</em> be stolen after a data breach, <a href="https://www.mcafee.com/blogs/privacy-identity-protection/how-to-protect-yourself-from-identity-theft-after-a-data-breach/">as one might naturally expect</a>, there doesn&rsquo;t yet exist any such recourse for <em>future</em> harms. These are all examples of why it is difficult to legally validate privacy violations, and things can get really subjective really fast.</p>
<p>Before I continue, I encourage you to read this paper (linked in <a href="#references">References</a>) if you&rsquo;re interested, lest I get carried away.</p>
<h2 id="defining-harm">Defining <em>harm</em></h2>
<p>Beyond financial penalties, in this space I don&rsquo;t see much dialogue about the personal repercussions of when privacy protections, well, don&rsquo;t protect.</p>
<p>The consequences and implications of the misuse or mishandling of personal data (that result from lapses in those protections) can be articulated as privacy <strong>&ldquo;harms&rdquo;</strong>. These harms describe a sobering aftermath of often deeply personal, real issues that affect humans (not users) and transcend fines and other legal penalties.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These harms describe a sobering aftermath of often deeply personal, real issues that affect humans (not users) and transcend fines and other legal penalties.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You&rsquo;ll see that these harms characterize relatable and sometimes existential concerns that may resonate with many or at least lead them to consider their significance, and hopefully reconsider how they think about privacy.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-harms">Types of harms</h2>
<p>The <em>Privacy Harms</em> typology outlines these harms as a means for courts to better understand and hopefully litigate privacy harms, however, they still serve as a guideline for any organization to understand what can come of privacy violations beyond legal repercussions.</p>
<p>All quotations will be taken from the paper unless otherwise explicitly mentioned.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/typology-of-harms.png"/> 
</figure>

<em>via Privacy Harms, Figure 1, page 831</em></p>
<h3 id="1-physical">1. Physical</h3>
<p>Physical harms are &ldquo;harms that result in bodily injury or death&rdquo;. Short, simple, and somber.
Personal information falling into the wrong hands can lead to violence that precipitates harm, whether that information is acquired intentionally or accidentally.</p>
<p>Physical harm resulting from privacy violations primarily threatens journalists and members of vulnerable or oppressed populations (such as the LGTBQ+ community and certain religions) but, ultimately, anyone can be affected:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1999-dec-05-mn-40632-story.html">The murder of Amy Boyer</a>: A man purchases personal information from a data broker/people-search site to stalk and eventually murder a woman he had never met.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.dailydot.com/upstream/pop-smoke-address/">The murder of Pop Smoke</a>: A famous rapper accidentally reveals his address in an Instagram story and is murdered during a home invasion that same night.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-economic">2. Economic</h3>
<p>An economic harm might involve &ldquo;monetary losses or a loss in the value of something.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Missed opportunities (indirect loss), such as a job offer, a loan, or other prospects with a financial element.</li>
<li>Immediate identity theft or the lingering potential for future identity theft (for example, after sensitive data is leaked in a data breach) - and the time and resources involved in dealing with the aftermath.</li>
<li>Stolen financial data (direct loss), such as account information or credit card numbers.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-reputational">3. Reputational</h3>
<p>&ldquo;Reputational harms involve injuries to an individual’s reputation and standing
in the community.&rdquo; These harms can &ldquo;impair a person’s ability
to maintain &lsquo;personal esteem in the eyes of others&rsquo; and can taint a person&rsquo;s
image&rdquo;. This is one of the more well-known harms when it comes to privacy, whether people may realize it or not.</p>
<p>Poor <a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/data-quality">data quality</a> (accuracy and correctness) can negatively impact a person&rsquo;s standing in society. Some examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Incorrect information in a credit report.</li>
<li>Poor &ldquo;data hygiene&rdquo; that results in incorrect data being propagated or indexed across the internet (in credit reports or on people search sites, for example) which can be difficult and lengthy to remove. Meanwhile, this bad data can spread and have negative implications for a person&rsquo;s public perception.</li>
</ul>
<p>By the same token, however, consider information that <em>is</em> true that might equally harm a person&rsquo;s reputation.</p>
<ul>
<li>This can involve invasion-of-privacy cases of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revenge_porn">&ldquo;revenge porn&rdquo;</a>, such as <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/mattdrange/2019/12/23/best-stories-of-the-decade-behind-peter-thiels-plan-to-destroy-gawker/?sh=25afb81072d9">Hulk Hogan&rsquo;s lawsuit against Gawker</a> in 2016, where the Hulkster (backed by Peter Thiel) bankrupted the tabloid &ldquo;news&rdquo; site that posted an illegally obtained sex-tape featuring him and his friend&rsquo;s wife.</li>
<li>In an extreme case in 2015, a <a href="https://money.cnn.com/2015/09/08/technology/ashley-madison-suicide/index.html">pastor took his own life</a> after Ashley Madison, the dating app he allegedly signed up for which is marketed towards married individuals looking for an affair, experienced a data massive data breach which exposed over 37 million users. Netflix has announced an <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/tv/other/new-netflix-series-reveals-scandalous-stories-behind-ashley-madison-hack/ar-AA1o2QTo">upcoming mini-series</a> about the breach.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-psychological">4. Psychological</h3>
<p>&ldquo;Psychological harms involve a range of negative mental responses&rdquo;, which can be generally
categorized into two sub-types:</p>
<ol>
<li>Emotional distress: &ldquo;painful or unpleasant feelings&rdquo;</li>
<li>Disturbance: &ldquo;disruption to tranquility and peace of mind&rdquo;</li>
</ol>
<p>Sinister online attacks like doxxing, death threats, revenge porn, <a href="https://www.dictionary.com/e/slang/brigading/">brigading</a> and others that violate or attempt to violate one&rsquo;s privacy can impose an immense psychological burden on victims. This burden may be in the form of fear (such as for one&rsquo;s safety), regret, shame, loss of self-worth, and various other negative emotions.</p>
<p>The authors also discuss the idea of &ldquo;disturbance&rdquo;, where victims experience &ldquo;unwanted intrusions that disturb tranquility, interrupt activities, sap time, and otherwise serve as a nuisance.&rdquo; An unfortunately common example of disturbance is the resulting barrage of phone calls or messages that a doxxing victim may receive after their information is posted online. These messages do not need to be threatening to constitute a disturbance, but the content of these messages may exacerbate the emotional distress that is caused.</p>
<h3 id="5-autonomy">5. Autonomy</h3>
<p>A harm against autonomy invovles the &ldquo;restricting, undermining, inhibiting, or unduly
influencing of people’s choices.&rdquo; This may entail preventing a user from making a choice for their cookie consent or data sharing preferences, for example, or otherwise tricking a user to make a choice that they did not intend or even outright denying which choices can be made or which controls are available to them.</p>
<p>This is heavily related, but not exclusive to, <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/how-to-spot-avoid-dark-patterns/">dark patterns</a>.
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/dark-patterns.png"/> 
</figure>

<em>via Krisztina Szerovay, <a href="https://uxknowledgebase.com/dark-patterns-3b41ed7a690e">UX Knowledge Base</a></em></p>
<p>Autonomy harms may manifest through user-facing mechanisms like cookie consent banners and preference centers, opt-out or privacy web forms, or other features that might solicit some type of input, where the service unfairly influences or manipulates the user&rsquo;s input. Sometimes, however, these mechanisms may not even provide a user the choice or option to control how their data is collected or shared, which the paper describes as a &ldquo;lack of control&rdquo; where users have no say.</p>
<p>Similarly, information popups and disclosures across a site are important to help a user understand the consequences of their use of the site or service. Inadequate, or worse: absent, notices are also harmful to users who may make decisions that contradict their privacy preferences.</p>
<h3 id="6-discrimination">6. Discrimination</h3>
<p>Discrimination harms are an extension of other harms which are founded on &ldquo;inequality and disadvantaging people based on gender, race, national origin, sexual orientation, age, group membership, or other characteristics or affiliations.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As the name suggests, marginalized communities are particularly affected by discrimination harms which &ldquo;thwart people’s ability to have an equal chance to obtain and keep jobs, to secure affordable insurance, to find housing, and to pursue other crucial life opportunities.&rdquo; Societal norms, increased surveilance, and unfair algorithms are some of the mechanisms that enable the undermining of privacy as it pertains to persons of marginalized groups that may lead to discrimination.</p>
<h3 id="7-relationship">7. Relationship</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.takingcharge.csh.umn.edu/what-do-we-mean-personal-relationships">Relationships</a> are a vital part of a healthy, functional life and society. Common types of relationships include friends, family, romantic partners, or even business associates (&ldquo;fiduciary relationships&rdquo;). This harm has two components:</p>
<ol>
<li>The &ldquo;[immediate] loss of confidentiality&rdquo; between partners</li>
<li>&ldquo;[In] the longer term, damage to the trust that is essential for the relationship&rdquo;</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="taking-harms-into-account-for-your-organization">Taking harms into account for your organization</h2>
<p>What kinds of harms might befall a user depend entirely on the context and scope of service  in use. A person signing up for a social media app to post memes of their cat may be subject to an entirely different set of potential harms compared to a person ordering a pizza with a food delivery app or a journalist sharing their geolocation data in an instant messenger app.</p>
<p>That is, the harms that will need to be proctected against will differ wildly by organization. It is vital to understand that these harms exist and map them to those that might be relevant to your users.</p>
<p>I believe taking these harms into account is a critical starting point for implementing an effective and empathetic privacy program across any organization that humanizes the user and safeguards privacy as a fundamental human right.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Citron, Danielle Keats and Solove, Daniel J., Privacy Harms (February 9, 2021). GWU Legal Studies Research Paper No. 2021-11, GWU Law School Public Law Research Paper No. 2021-11, 102 Boston University Law Review 793 (2022), Available at SSRN: <a href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=3782222">https://ssrn.com/abstract=3782222</a> or <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3782222">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3782222</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
